Twice-Cooked Pork
Sorry for the wait.
（相生祐子(あいおいゆうこ)）おまたせ
こんな物しか できないけど
I can only make this.
はいっ
Here.
Wow, awesome!
（長野原(ながのはら)みお）わあ すごっ
ホイコーローじゃん
It's twice-cooked pork.
I'm really hungry, so this is perfect.
超おなか減ってたから助かる
I put something in for a hidden taste.
隠し味に ちょっとした物を
入れたんだけど 分かるかな？
I wonder if you can tell.
Having a hidden taste makes it sound like the real thing.
隠し味なんて
ずいぶん本格的じゃん
（祐子）アハハハ
（みお）いただきまーす
I'm digging in!
It only has the miso flavour, or rather,
みその味しかしないというか
隠し味が 隠れなさすぎというか
the hidden taste is not so hidden, or rather...
No, instead, the more you chew it,
いや むしろ この隠し味が―
the hidden taste gets worse, or rather...
かめばかむほど
相当まずくしているというか
I'm really against this hidden taste!
これ 本格的にアゲインスト！
Nichijou 23
おっ おおっ
こりゃ なかなか
This is actually pretty good...
Mio-chan, Mio-chan!
（祐子）みおちゃん みおちゃん
（祐子）エヘヘ
TL note: Kappa, literally meaning "river-child", is a water sprite found in Japanese folklore.
is cool, isn't it?
（みお）
何だ？ こりゃ“KAPPA(カッパ)”？
What the hell is this?
Kappa?
is cool, isn't it?
Why a kappa all of the sudden?
なぜ 今 カッパなんだ？
しかも カッコいいでしょって
Moreover, what does she mean by "is cool, isn't it?"...
うーん うーん
でも 今度 描くのは―
But...
Next time, I might want to draw something in fantasy that's interesting and strong.
ファンタジー色 強くても
面白いかもしれないなあ
Something like a Daidarabotchi and a kappa.
TL note: Daidarabotchi is a gigantic demon in Japanese mythology.
デイダラボッチとカッパ とかね
Kappa... Heh, I guess he will be the "uke".
TL note: In yaoi, "uke" refers to the more feminine partner.
カッパ  受けかな？
Kappa, kappa, huh?
カッパ カッパねえ
Kappa...
カッパ カッパッパー
Kappapaa... pa... pa...
パッ パッ“Parasite(パラサイト)”っつってね
Parasite.
With this, maybe we can just play picture shiritori.
この流れで 絵しりとりでも
やりますか
Yukko.
（みお）ゆっこ
Thanks.
はい …と　おっ？
Parashite?
TL note: In Japanese, parasite is read as "parasaito", but Yukko read it as "parashite".
（祐子）
〝Ｐａｒａｓｉｔｅ(パラシテ)〞？
パラシテって
こういう生き物なの？　おっ
This is what a parashite's meant to be like?
Having this arrow means...
この矢印があるってことは…
I see. She's inviting me to a game of picture shiritori.
さては 絵しりとりを
誘ってるな？
I'll accept it.
受けてあげようじゃないの
Hmm... Parashite...
ええ パラシテねえ
テ テ…　ええ よしっ
"Te"... "Te"... Okay.
So big!
I didn't have time!
（みお）
デカッ！ しかも天狗(てんぐ)って
Moreover, a "tengu"...
She read parasite's "to" as "te".
Parasiteの“te(ト)”を
“te(テ)”って読んだろ？
まあ いいか 天狗ね
Oh, well.
A "tengu," huh?
天狗　ぐ ぐ ぐ…
"Tengu"... "gu"... "gu"... "gu"...
"Gu-"!
ぐっ！ ウ… ウソでしょ？
N-No way!
“ＴＥＮＧＯ(テンゴ)！”
Tengo!
What the hell is a "tengo"?!
テンゴって何だよ
テンゴって
What's a "tengo"?!
No! Wait a minute!
いやっ 引っかけ！
There's no way a high school student would make such a childish mistake.
こんな稚拙な間違い
高校生がするわけない
だって天狗を絵で見せてから
わざわざ文字を書いてるし
I mean, she already drew a picture of a
tengu and still wrote down what it was.
I don't get it.
意味が分からない　ううんっ
I don't really understand, but...
何か腑(ふ)に落ちないけど―
I guess I'll go with "go" here.
ここは あえて
“ゴ”でいきますかあ
ハアッ
はい
Here.
Draw smaller!
（祐子）わああ 何？
このアンニュイな“ＧＯＫＵ(ゴクウ)”
What's with this Goku drawn out of boredom?
TL note: Goku is a character from a classical Chinese novel "Journey To The West".
あ？ あれ 悟空(ごくう)？
Huh... Wait... Goku?
I'm pretty sure I drew a tengu just now...
さっき 私が描いたのって
天狗だったはず
Well, I can understand how she could mistake "gu" for "go".
まっ“ぐ”って考えて―
“ご”になるのは
分かる気がするけどね
I'll get juice from her later for this.
こりゃ あとでジュースだな
Now, it's "u"... "u"... "u"... Okay!
じゃ さて“う”ね
う う…　よしっ
Draw smaller!
I can't draw very well!
A sea urchin?
TL note: Sea urchin is "uni", and rabbit is "usagi", or "usa" for short, in Japanese.
Draw smaller!
I can't draw very well!
ウニ？ いやっ ウサ
Draw smaller!
I can't draw very well!
cow
No, a rabbit.
I can't draw very well!
cow
“ＵＳＩ(ウシ)”かよっ！
I can't draw very well!
cow
It's a cow?!
TL note: Cow is "ushi" in Japanese.
I can't draw very well!
cow
This cow is beyond terrible...
この牛は ひどすぎだ
はい
Here.
（祐子）うおお
“Shita(シタ)”舌と きたかあ
Tongue! She came at me with the tongue!
TL note: In Japanese, tongue is "shita".
Then, it's "ta".
じゃあ“タ”だな
タ タ… タクシーと
"Ta"... "ta"...
Taxi... Ta...
はい
W-Why are you doing this?!
な… なんでだよ！
If you write it like this, it isn't a taxi.
これじゃあ
タクシーじゃなくて―
It's a taxy!
“TAXY(タクスィー)”だよおお！
I'm just going to write down whatever works.
もう 適当に描いとくか
Oh, seafood has started to come up!
（祐子）おお
業界用語と きたもんだ
shisu
She's really up for it.
さてはノリノリだな？
はい はい はいーっと
Okay, okay, okay.
Oh, no!
しまった！
これじゃあ 負けじゃん
uperman
I'll lose like this!
TL note: There is no word in Japanese beginning with the sound "n", so you lose if you use a word ending with the kana "n" in a game of shiritori.
uperman
No, this... I just have to do this...
いやっ まだ
ここを こーすれば…
Here.
はい
（祐子）フフン フン
X
Go Soccer Club
Go Soccer Club 3
Ah, there's nothing to do.
（大工健三郞(だいくけんざぶろう)）うわあ　暇だなあ
There's nothing to do, Sekiguchi.
暇だなあ 関口(せきぐち)
フウ
Okay, Sekiguchi, let's have an "Isse no se" match!
TL note: "Isse no se" is a Japanese numbers game played using both hands.
よし！ 関口
いっせーのせで勝負だ
I'll start!
俺から いくぞ
Isse no two!
いっせーの２(に)
Sekiguchi...
関口　暇なんだし
たまには つきあえよ
There's nothing to do, anyway. Can't you play with me sometimes?
President.
（関口ユリア）部長
ああっ 関口
Sekiguchi...
Nichijou 24
I forgot my homework and was made to stand in the hallway, Mogami river. By Yukko.
ハア
I can't believe I have to stand in the hallway just because I forgot my homework today...
（祐子）
きょうび 宿題を忘れたぐらいで
廊下に立たされるとは
How should I spend this time, Mogami river. By Yukko.
Wai-
ちょっ み… みんな
E-Everyone! It's a deer... It's a deer...
し… 鹿 鹿
W-Why is the principal is trying to catch the deer...?
な… なんで校長が鹿を
W-Wai- Principal... D-Deer...
ちょっ ちょっ
校長　し… 鹿
（校長先生）フンッ
（校長）どわああっ
（祐子）ええ
（校長）だあ！ ううっ
Principal!
（祐子）校長！
W-Wait, everyone... The principal's... dying...
ちょ… ちょっと みんな
校長が ひん死
（祐子）あっ あ…
（校長）ふん
That's a... shika senbei?!
TL note: Shika senbei are rice crackers specially made to feed deer.
（祐子）あれは 鹿せんべい！
（校長）どわああっ
W-Wai- Everyone, the principal is d-dyin-
（校長）あちゃ あちゃ
（祐子）
みんな 校長が 死 死…
（祐子）起きた
He got up.
He climbed up!
（祐子）登った！
（校長）とおっ！
He jumped!
（祐子）飛んだ！
And falls down just like that!
そのまま落ちた！
He climbed up again!
また登ったああ
ああっ ハアッ
ハア ハア
He climbed down!
（祐子）降りた！
H-He's in a deadlock!
（祐子）
手… 手詰まりだ　ううっ
Principal!
（祐子）校長！
Principal...
（祐子）校長…
ああ　校長
Wai- Everyone... Death... Principal... Death...
みんな　DEATH(デス) 校長　DEATH
（祐子）立ったあ
（校長）ふんっ！
（校長）えいっ
うぐっ
Uh... Wai- Um... Uh...
（祐子）ああ ちょっ えっと
いやあ…
Wai- Everyone, listen!
ちょっ みんな　聞いて
Uh... Um... P-Prin...
ああ ええっと…
くっ こ… こう
Um... Prin...
ああっ こう
フウーッ
Nothing new to report from the hallway!
廊下は異常ありません！
Those were the true words that came from the bottom of her heart.
（ナレーター）
それは 心の奥底から出た
本当の言葉だった
They were by no means to cover up for the principal,
決して 校長を かばおうとか―
nor because explaining it would be too troublesome.
説明するのが面倒くさかったとか
そういうのではない
Nothing like that.
もしかしたら さっきまで
死闘を演じていた勇者たちに―
Maybe she just wanted to show respect to the
heroes who had just performed a fight to the death.
敬意を表したかったのかもしれない
（祐子）ああ ウフッ
It's too early to gather the early-summer rain, Mogami river.
No idea what it means.
（祐子）意味不明
10 Yen Soccer
Okay, then. Mio-chan will be the referee.
（祐子）よーし
じゃあ みおちゃんが審判ね
You don't need a referee for ten yen soccer.
10円サッカーに
審判は いらないじゃん
You don't understand, do you?
分かってないなあ
こういうのは気分だよ　気分！
It's all about the feeling, the feeling.
Now, kick off!
さあ！ キックオフ
I guess it can't be helped.
しょうがないなあ
Come at me from any angle!
どっからでも かかってこーい
Okay...
（水上麻衣(みなかみまい)）じゃあ
First comes rock, next comes paper. Rockscispaper doesn't count,
（はかせ･東雲(しののめ)なの）
♪ 最初はグー　その次パー
rock, paper, scissors!
I-
（はかせ）サ…
（なの）ガブッ
Chomp.
I love you.
（はかせ）サランヘヨ
Shinonome Institute
Nichijou 25
What should I do?
（なの）どうしよう
I caught a cockroach...
ゴキブリ 捕まえちゃった
C-Carefully...
（なの）し… 慎重に
とにかく慎重にいこう
Anyway, I'll have to do it carefully...
I have to make sure this disgusting root of evil doesn't spread in the house again.
この気持ちの悪い
悪の権化を―
二度と この家に
はびこらせないように―
A plan... I have to go with the most perfect plan...
策を… 最善の策を練らなきゃ
ああっ　殺虫スプレー！
Ah, pesticide spray!
いや ダメ
No, I can't.
It's not a one-hit-kill, so there's a chance that it will just run away.
一撃必殺じゃないから そのまま
逃げられる可能性があるし―
Most of all...
それに なにより
I don't want to see it squirm!
あれが もがくさまを見たくない
Ah, that's right!
あっ そうだ　洗剤は？
What about detergent?
I'll cover the tea table with detergent to seal its movement, and then pinpoint it directly!
ちゃぶ台の周りに洗剤を
まき散らして―
動きを封じてから
ピンポイントで やつを狙う
はっ と… 飛ぶ！ うっ
I-It will fly!
With nowhere to run, it'll definitely fly!
（なの）
逃げ場をなくしたやつらは
必ず飛ぶ
When it flies, it's over.
飛んだら最後 人を目がけて
やみくもに突っこんでくる
It'll blindly aim somewhere and hit people!
If it were to hit my body... or hit my face...!
もし これが体に…
い… いやっ
顔なんかに当たったら
No, wait...
いや ちょ 待っ…
I-If this was to get inside... get inside my mouth...
も… もし く… 口の中に…
口の中に これが入ってきたら…
ハアッ ハアッ ハアッ
It's a one-shot rock and roll!
（なの）
１発でロックンロール！
ぐはっ 最高のギグだ
なすすべがない
This is the worst kind of uneasiness.
I don't have any other choice.
The choice of lifting this bowl up might kill me!
このおわんを上げた時点で
選択肢は 死か死ぬかの―
Death or die!
DEATH(デス) or(オア) DIE(ダイ)！
（なの）あ… あれを
あれをやるしか
There's...
Trash
There's no choice but to do that...
（阪本(さかもと)）ん？ 何やってんだ？
What are you doing?
あっ さ… 阪本さん
助けてください
S-Sakamoto-san!
Please save me!
I-Inside this, there is a r-roach... a roach.
こ… この中に―
ゴ… ゴキ ゴキ…
What?
（阪本）何だ？　うっ
ひょっとしてゴキブリか？
Could it be a cockroach?
I guess it can't be helped.
（阪本）しょうがねえなあ
よしっ 任せろ
All right.
Leave it to me.
That'll save me.
助かります　ふうっ
（なの）ううう
（阪本）うーん おいっ！
Hey.
あっ はい
Yes?
（阪本）何やってるんだよ？
What are you doing?
捕ってやるから
おわんを上げろよ
I'll get it, so lift the bowl.
はい？
Yes?
No, I'm saying lift the bowl.
（阪本）いやっ だから―
おわんを持ち上げろよ
じゃないと捕れねえだろうが
Otherwise, I can't get it.
もう　おい！
Hey!
W-What are you saying?!
な… 何言ってるんですか？
How could I lift the seal on the root of evil?!
私が悪の権化の封印を
解くなんて
This is Pandora's box!
これはパンドラの箱なんですよ
The moment I lift it up, it's death or die!
上げた時点で
DEATH or DIEです
No, no, no.
（阪本）いや いや いや
How am I supposed to get it without lifting up the bowl?!
おわんを上げずに
どうやって捕ればいいんだよ
Lift it up yourself!
自分で上げてください
As if I can!
（阪本）上げれるか！
W-What should I do?
（なの）
ど… どうしよう　阪本さんは
どっかへ行っちゃうし
Sakamoto-san has gone somewhere...
Nano!
What's today's snack?
（はかせ）
なの 今日の おやつ何？
Ah, good timing!
ああっ グッタイミーンッ
The professor is not bothered by bugs either, so surely she can...
（なの）はかせも
虫とか平気だから きっと
Professor, i-it'd be nice if you could get rid of t-this cockroach inside this bowl!
はかせ こ… この
おわんの中のゴキブリ―
し… 処理してもらえると
助かるんですけど
Sure.
いいよ
R-Rock and roll!
（なの）
ロロロ ロックンロール！
うっ す… すいません
じゃあ お願いして
Sorry, then I shall leave it to you.
It's okay.
オーケーです　じゃあ
１発で やっちゃうからねえ
I'll do it in one shot!
メ－ン！
Men!
TL note: "Men" is what you say after successfully hitting your opponent's head in kendo.
Oh, I hit the wrong one.
あっ 間違えちゃった
アハッ アハハハッ
（なの）
わ… 私が… 私が こんなに
真剣に悩んでるのに
I-I'm... I'm seriously worried here, but this person is... this person is...
この人って人は…
もう はかせなんて大嫌いです！
Seriously, I hate you, professor!
（なの）
ああっ な… 泣く？
You're going to cry?
あっ な… なーんてウソですよ
イヤですねえ もう
It's just a joke!
Geez, there's no way I would hate you.
私が はかせを
嫌いなわけないじゃないですか
Professor, I love you.
はかせ  大好きですよ
あはっ
なの！
Nano!
Geez, professor.
もう はかせったら
Nano!
（はかせ）なの！
Now, it's time to rock and roll!
（ナレーター）
さあ ロックンロールの始まりだ
If You Count To 10
Hey, it's hot, so can I get out?
ねえ 熱いから出ていい？
Huh?
ええっ？　今
入ったばっかりじゃないですか
We just got in.
But it's become hot...
でも 熱くなったから
Then let's get out after a count to ten.
じゃあ 10まで言ったら
出ることにしましょうか
Twenty log root ten!
20ログ ルート10！
Huh?
You said we can get out once we count to ten.
10まで言ったから出ていい？
Uh... Um...
えっ ええっと
You have to say "One, two"...
“イーチ ニイ”って
言わなきゃダメです
Go Soccer Club 4
What's with everyone?
なーんだよ　みんな
塾だからって帰っちゃうしさあ
Just because they have cram school, they all leave.
関口だって
つまんないよなあ
Sekiguchi, you're bored as well, right?
Huh?
あれ？ そういえば
関口も 塾 行ってなかったっけ？
Come to think of it, didn't you go to cram school, too?
You've got to be kidding!
（大工）ウソッ
Nichijou 26
うまっ！
Delicious!
Yukko, how's the curry?
ゆっこ　カレーどう？
Yeah, it's almost done.
うん　もうすぐ できるよ
I'm quite hungry.
もう かなり
グーペコになってきたよ
Yeah, me, too!
超 私も
Mai-chan, how are things over there?
麻衣ちゃん　そっちは どう？
I foresee a big one.
大物の予感
（みお）エヘヘヘッ
こりゃ ごちそうだな
This will be a feast.
All right! It seems like it's ready.
よーし　もう いい感じだろう
よっと
Thanks for waiting.
へい お待ち 超美味(びみ)
スーパーカレー 完成の巻なのだ
The extremely delicious super-curry is complete.
（みお）こっちは
もう ちょっと かかるかなあ
I think it will take a little longer over here.
We should have started these before the curry.
カレー作る前に
仕込んどけば よかったね
Well, they say,
まあっ 赤子 泣いても
フタ取るなっつってね
"Even if a baby is crying from hunger, don't remove the lid".
ああっ マヨネーズ
持ってくれば よかったよ
Ah, we should have brought mayonnaise.
You really need mayonnaise for curry.
カレーには
マヨネーズだよね やっぱ
M-Mayo-
マ… マヨ マ…
Yukko, what do you like with curry?
ゆっこは何派？
Just kidding.
お… おええっ なんつって
あ… いや ち… 違くて
No... It's not like that...
T-This is... not what you think...
こ… これは
そういうんじゃなくて
I still have- Look, I still have tokoroten!
TL note: Tokoroten are strips of gelidium jelly (agar).
まだ ほ… ほら
トコロテンもあるし
ト… トコロテン　なんつ…
T-Tokoroten... Just kidding.
What is your...
（みお）お前の
M-Mio-chan...
み… みおちゃん
What is your...
（みお）お前のは
What is the colour of your blood?!
（みお）
お前の血は何色だあ！
イヤーッ！
イヤーッ
（みお）イヤーッ！
Sorry, Mai-chan!
ごめん 麻衣ちゃん
We've lost the curry and rice we were having for lunch.
（祐子）昼食のカレーも
米もなくなった
Mai-chan...
（みお）麻衣ちゃん？
There's still tokoroten, if you want...
トコロテンならあるけど
ああ！ 麻衣ちゃーん
Mai-chan!
Release.
（麻衣）リリース
Well, then. There's one tokoroten here.
（祐子）さて ここに
１つのトコロテンがあります
Only one?!
１個だけなの？
I think we should take turns eating it.
これを みんなで回して
食べたいと思います
However, as we are to blame, Mai-chan, you should start.
…が 非は 私と
みおちゃんにありますので―
まずは 麻衣ちゃんから どうぞ
Rock, paper, scissors!
（祐子･みお）じゃんけん ぽん
（祐子）よっしゃ！
（みお）ぐわっ
一口で 全部 食べるなんて
オチだけは やめてよね
Just make sure you don't eat all of it in one bite!
That's upsetting to me... I'm not a demon, you know.
心外だなあ
私も鬼じゃないんだから
そんじゃ
お先に いただきまーす
I'll dig in first.
（祐子）ブッ フハッ
ゴホッ　ゴホッ ゴホッ
ゲホッ ゲホッ ゲホッ ゲホッ
ハア
I choked.
むせちゃった
（みお）うりゃあ－っ！
（祐子）てはあっ ううう
（みお）おりゃあ－っ！
（祐子）ぐふっ
（みお）ええいっ！
（祐子）ぐははっ
（みお）おりゃああ
（祐子）あのっ ああっ
（みお）せいやっ！
（祐子）あはあっ
（みお）わああっ
That's right! Let's play cards!
そうだ　トランプやろうか？
やんない！
Let's not!
If things continue this way,
（祐子）このままだと
残念キャンプで終わるよ
this'll end as a disappointing camping trip!
Let's play cards at the very last moment and give it a happy ending!
最後の最後はトランプして―
ハッピーエンドでシメでしょ
That's right!
そうだ！
Oh, what's up?
おうっ どったの？
I totally forgot!
すっかり忘れてた
Adults drink alcohol at times like these, right?
大人は こういうとき
お酒を飲むじゃん？
T-That's right.
そ… そだね
Hey, Mai-chan, don't you agree?
ねえ 麻衣ちゃんも
そう思わない？
Actually, I brought some!
実は 私も
持ってきてたんだよね
ま… まさか みおちゃん
T-That can't be, Mio-chan.
フフフッ
そのまさかだよ
That's right.
A delinquent.
悪だ　ここに悪がいる
There's a delinquent here!
Tada!
ジャーン！
Vinegar
A-Any bottle is fine!
（みお）な…
なんぼのもんじゃーい
Mio-chan stop it! You'll die!
（祐子）みおちゃん
やめなよ　死ぬよ
We still have Mai-chan's left!
（祐子）
まだ 麻衣ちゃんのが
あるじゃん
This is cider.
（麻衣）これ サイダー
Sign: サイダー Cider
（バディ）ワウッ！
（２人）プハーッ
Word Of The Day
MILK
Exit the bath, drink milk, act drunk.
I'm a peso!
（ペソ）ペソでーす
（10円玉）10円です
I'm ten yen!
I'm wadoukaichin!
TL note: Wadoukaichin is Japan's first circulated coinage, minted in 708 CE.
（和同開珎(わどうかいちん)）和同開珎です
No, no.
（ペソ）ノーノー
人の価値は おカネじゃないでーす
A person's value is not measured by money!
ハハハッ ハハハオッ
The next Nichijou is the seventh!
Narration:     Koyama Rikiya
次回の「日常」は
第７話　お楽しみに
Look forward to it!